Guide to the Records of the Association for the Relief of Respectable, Aged and Indigent Females in New York City 1813-1883 MS 801
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Records of the Association for the Relief of Respectable, Aged and Indigent Females in New York City
1813-1883
MS 801
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
0.417 Linear feet (1 box)
Eight volumes of records including pensioners’ rolls, 1813-1832, 1840-1860; meeting minutes, 1814-1817; Advisory Committee minutes, 1867-1883; journal of visits, 1839-1843; expenditures, 1814; receipts, 1849-1862; accounts for extra fuel, 1844-1862; and death register, 1838-1875.
Provenance
Purchased January 1976.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Historical Note
The Association for the Relief of Respectable, Aged and Indigent Females was formed in the autumn of 1813, organized the following February, and incorporated on 10 March 1815 to aid widows of the recent War of 1812 and the more distant American Revolution, women “who once enjoyed a good degree of affluence,” but were by then “reduced to poverty by the vicissitudes of Providence.”
A subscription begun in 1833 (to which John Jacob Astor donated $5,000 and Peter G. Stuyvesant gave three property lots) allowed the construction in 1837-38 of a four-story brick asylum at 226 East 20th Street (since demolished) to accommodate about one hundred pensioners and association officers. The building provided “a place of comfort to persons of refined sensibilities,” unlike “the common almshouse, filled as it usually [was] with the dregs of society.” An infirmary was added in 1845.
As the Association’s charitable activities expanded, the need for a larger home led to the construction of the extant 891 Amsterdam Avenue, designed by the noted architect Richard Morris Hunt. First occupied in June 1883 (effectively after the records in this collection end), the building formally opened in December during the Association’s seventieth anniversary celebrations that year. The residence accepted any respectable woman above age sixty, provided she was not a Roman Catholic and surrendered any personal property to the Association along with an entrance fee of $150.
The Association operated as late as 1974 — by then it was known as the “Association Residence Nursing Home” or the “Association Residence for Women” — when its occupants were relocated to another facility in anticipation of the construction of a modern building. This never happened, and the Association dissolved. The City of New York acquired the Amsterdam Avenue property in 1978, and after a period of decline, the structure was rehabilitated and now functions as the largest hostel in North America.
For further information, see The Constitution, and First and Second Annual Reports of the Proceedings of the Association for the Relief of Respectable, Aged, Indigent Females (New York: J. Seymour, 1815); Rev. John F. Richmond, New York and its Institutions, 1609-1872 (New York: E. B. Treat, 1872); and the New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission’s designation report LP-1280 for the Association Residence for Respectable Aged Indigent Females (Association Residence for Women), 891 Amsterdam Avenue.
Scope and Contents
This small collection spans the first eighty years of the existence of the Association for the Relief of Respectable, Aged and Indigent Females in New York City, from its inception in 1813 through its move, in 1883, to a substantial (and, ultimately, final) home at 891 Amsterdam Avenue. Due to the significant breaks in coverage, these records are best consulted in conjunction with the Association’s published annual reports; the New-York Historical Society Library holds the years 1815-1871 (with gaps) under call number F128 HV1447 .N5 A87.
Arrangement
The eight small volumes in this collection are housed in a single box. They are individually foldered and arranged in two series:
Series I: Expenditures, Receipts, and Meeting Minutes
Series II: Pensioner and Asylum records
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
Printed copies of the Association’s annual reports for the years 1815-1871 (with gaps) are shelved under call number F128 HV1447 .N5 A87.
Association for the Relief of Respectable Aged Indigent Females; Accounts.; Charities -- New York (State) -- New York.; Death registers; Journals (notebooks); Minutes.; New York (N.Y.); New York (N.Y.) -- Social conditions -- 19th century; Older women -- New York (State) -- New York.; Poor women -- New York (State) -- New York.; Women in charitable work -- New York (State) -- New York.
- Series I: Expenditures, Receipts, and Meeting Minutes
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes the earliest records of the Association in the form of expenditures (1814) and meeting minutes (1814-1817) bound in a volume labeled “ Minutes of | The Ladies Society | For the Relief of Respectable | Indigent Aged Females | 1814” (Folder 1). Advisory committee meeting minutes span 1867-1883 (Folders 3-4), after when the Association moved its operations from the asylum at 226 East 20th Street to the new building at 891 Amsterdam Avenue. A separate volume records receipts (1849-1862) and accounts for extra fuel (1844-1850) (Folder 2).
  - Expenditures (1814) and meeting minutes (1814-1817) [labeled vol. 2] (Folder 1)
  - Receipts (1849-1862) and accounts for extra fuel (1844-1850) [labeled vol. 6], 1844-1862 (Folder 2)
  - Advisory committee meeting minutes [labeled vol. 7], 1867-1870 (Folder 3)
  - Advisory committee meeting minutes [labeled vol. 8], 1870-1883 (Folder 4)
- Series II: Pensioner and Asylum Records
  This series includes rolls of pensioners visited by Association members before and after the opening of the asylum at 226 East 20th Street. The roll for 1813-1832 (Folder 5) records each pensioners’ name, age, religious affiliation, the name of the Association member in charge of their case, and, in some instances, their date of death. The roll for 1840-1860 (Folder 6) groups pensioners by the name of the Association member who cared for them. A separate register of deaths occurring in the asylum covers the years 1838-1875 (Folder 7). The Weekly Visiting Committee’s book records conditions in the asylum for the period 1839-1843 (Folder 8).
  - Pensioners' roll [labeled vol. 1], 1813-1832 (Folder 5)
  - Pensioners' roll [labeled vol. 5], 1840-1860 (Folder 6)
  - Death register [labeled vol. 3], 1838-1875 (Folder 7)
  - Weekly Visiting Committee’s Book [labeled vol. 4], 1839-1843 (Folder 8)